Guide to the Consumer Reports. Leland Gordon papers, 1931-1987 and undated RL.11812
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Leland Gordon papers
1931-1987 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11812
1.2 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Leland Gordon was Professor of economics at Denison University who served on the Board of Directors of Consumers Union from 1942-1949. The Leland Gordon papers include correspondence, manuscript of papers and book chapter drafts for Economics for Consumers, conference proceedings and other printed materials. Topics include consumer education and protection, consumption, economic aspects of burial and funeral practices, packaging and labeling of products, weights and measures, and World War II-era wartime economies. Institutions represented in the collection include Denison University, the National Council of Churches, Office of Price Administration, and Stephens College. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Personal and Professional Files; Economics for Consumers
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Leland Gordon was Professor of economics at Denison University who served on the Board of Directors of Consumers Union from 1942-1949.
Leland James Gordon was born in 1897 in Minnesota. He attended the University of Pennsylvania's Wharton School and received a doctorate in 1928. Gordon was professor of economics at Denison University (1931-1963) where he founded the Weights and Measures Research Center in 1955. He served on the Consumers Union's National Advisory Committee from 1940 and on the Board of Directors from 1942-1949, resigning during a dispute over the direction of the organizationinstitution. Gordon wrote a pioneering textbook on consumer economics, Economics for Consumers (1939) which remained in print for seven editions. Gordon died in 1982.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Leland Gordon papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports. Arthur Kallet papers
Consumer Reports. Colston E. Warne papers
Consumer Reports. James Mendenhall scrapbook
J. Walter Thompson Company. Advertising vertical file
Collection Overview
The Leland Gordon papers include correspondence, manuscript of papers and book chapter drafts for Economics for Consumers, conference proceedings and other printed materials. Topics include consumer education and protection, consumption, economic aspects of burial and funeral practices, packaging and labeling of products, weights and measures, and World War II-era wartime economies. Institutions represented in the collection include Denison University, the National Council of Churches, Office of Price Administration, and Stephens College.
Consumers -- United States; Consumer advocacy; Consumer education; consumer protection; Economics -- Study and teaching -- United States; Economics -- History -- 20th century; Gordon, Leland James, 1897-; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; United States. Office of Price Administration
- Personal and Professional Files, 1931-1987; 1
  - Consumer conferences, 1939-1942 (Box 1)
  - Consumer Economics (course at Denison University)--Reading list, annotated bibliography, 1948-1967 (Box 1)
  - Consumers' Research/Consumers Union, 1931-1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1937-1987; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Denison University/Office of Price Administration (OPA)--Community Consumer Program, 1942 (Box 1)
  - National Council of Churches, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Joint Meeting, Christian Understanding of Life and Death as Related to Funeral-Burial Costs and Practices
  - Paper--The Function of the Consumer in a Free Choice Society, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Papers, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
    Includes: Fair Packaging and Labeling--When?; Second National Survey of State Weights and Measures Legislation; Weights and Measures and the Consumer
  - Papers and articles, 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    Includes: Consumer Economics as an Introductory Course; Consumer Protection in a War Economy; Economic Education for Family Living; Economics for College Consumers; The Consumer Movement; Watch Your Weights and Measures in War Time
  - Stephens College--Consumer Education Division national conferences, 1936-1942; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Economics for Consumers, 6th edition, 1959-1971 and undated; 2
  - 1. The Consumer in a Free Society chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 2. The Compexity of Consumer Demand chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 5. Custom-made Wants chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 6. Ceremonial Custom-made Wants chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 7. Conspicuous Consumption and Emulation chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 8. Fashion-made Wants chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 9. Seller-made Wants: Advertising chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 10. A Consumer View of Advertising chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 2)
  - 11. The Marketing and Pricing Processes chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 3)
  - 18. How to Become a Better Buyer chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 3)
  - 19. To Own or Rent? chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 3)
  - 20. Buying Protection: Principles of Insurance chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - 22. Buying Investments: Some Guidelines for Small Investors chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 3)
  - 25. Measurement Laws Help Consumers chapter notes, 1970-1971 and undated (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1971 (Box 3)